ac is on
welcome to meditating with uh john
riveki we do this
live stream every morning at 9 30 a.m
eastern time
with mondays alternating between a new
lesson called the dharma day
and review lesson of the whole ecology
practices called the pi
day yesterday would have been a dharma
day but it was a holiday in canada so we
didn't meet
we will have our next dharma day next
monday and we're going to start
uh the western wisdom tradition uh we'll
start with the wisdom of hypatia
if you're joining us for the first time
you're most welcome
for previous lessons and sits go to the
district uh the description in this
video and you'll find links
i recommend strongly that you go and do
lesson one right away
and then do one or two lessons um uh
every week
and keep meeting with us regularly and
soon you'll find yourself uh
integrated into the senga and to uh the
ecology practices you're most welcome
i would ask all of you to please help me
reach as many people as possible by
liking
uh the stream decreases visibility in
the youtube algorithm
at the end of every session uh there's
there's q
a please limit your questions at that
time to anything from
the entire ecology of practices for more
encompassing questions
we have a live stream every third friday
of the month at 3pm eastern time
in which you can ask questions then
i think that's everything we're gonna we
need to do right now uh we'll have
some time for a few questions at the end
today
and so please set your phones on do not
disturb get yourself in position
as always we will begin by a bit of
chanting then we'll go into our silent
silence
we'll begin when i say begin
begin
[Music]
one
can you silence it
so
you
[Music]
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice
with your video consciousness cognition
character and communitas
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
now we have time for a few questions
um this is from fsck
i attended some bilateral stem
stimulation of a past
meditation last week and noticed a time
dilation type effect
is there a term for this in any buddhist
school or sec
uh do you mean for the time dilation
effect not
i mean i don't know if there's a
technical term for this that i'm aware
of
that doesn't mean very much because
there are a lot of sex there's a lot of
different lineages
um i do know that prime dilation
is a standard feature of
flow and uh i've argued with leo ferraro
and area bennett uh that flow is an
insight cascade and there's lots of
evidence that what's happening
um in insight is a radical
and rapid restructuring of uh neuronal
pattern
of firing between the two hemispheres
and that makes sense uh that that would
bring with it
what we know in the flow state you get
one of the widely reported effects in
flow states
and then the overlapping mystical states
is time dilation
um effects that happen i suspect
this has to do with the same kind of
thing that's happening
in insight but magnified uh which is
what's what you consider relevant and
salient what's foregrounded and
backgrounded
is rapidly being restructured and
altered um
and so uh psychological time
even psychological space when you do
some work on mental imagery
uh seems to be measured uh not the way
we measure measure sort of
just sort of i don't know what's called
physical time uh which is
you know standard units of measurement
psychological time is measured in terms
of
increments of meaning and when you're
getting massive restructuring
it's going to alter your sense of time
significantly that's what i suspect
is happening so i think the time
dilation uh
is a
effect probably a side effect i don't
know if it itself is adaptive
although it has the reflective
adaptation of getting you to step aside
uh
from sort of your normal perspective to
do a bit of the view from above
which we'll talk about when we do uh the
wisdom of my patient
but i suspect that um the real
adaptive benefits are from
the restructuring of hemispheric
integration dynamic
integration and the facilitation
of reframing capacities insight
capacities
that's going on which is of course at
the heart of the passana um
so um that's my best shot at trying to
uh answer your question i hope that was
helpful
uh karima good to see you again karima
any more insights from your alexio
davina a few days on presents it seems
in silence it has the loudest voice
yeah so um
i think uh the reason why you i'm
pausing here
there's no attempt to uh exemplify
science uh i guess it just happened
is because um the work i've been doing
uh
with christopher matt's master pietro on
we're putting together an
anthology called inner and outer
dialogues in which people are writing
about all of these emerging biological
practices
um and in some of chris's work
uh and then in some overlapping work
um i think from
uh thomas and elizabeth and almost
pascal
many people in here are talking about um
and chris does it really explicitly and
beautifully as it always does
how there's a degree of of silence
that plays an important role it's not
silence as the privation of speech
it is the silence that takes you into
that which makes all speech possible
and this is also something that's spoken
of in the neoplatonic christian
which we'll talk about when we get into
the wisdom of hypatia which is
when you get what whatever presencing is
that coming from
you know from the invisible into the
indivisible so from deep sorry from the
invisible to the visible
from the indeterminate to the
determinant that realization
of intelligibility whatever that is
coming from is not itself
intelligible there's no logos to it
so it itself cannot be put into speech
because
it is the grounding of the
intelligibility the patterns
of realness and realization upon which
speech is grounded and depends
and so therefore as we as our as we
conform
to that sourcing of intelligibility
we move into its silence but it's
different it's not the silence that is
the privation of speech as i said
it is the silence that is exactly taking
us into what ground speech
and if you'll allow me without something
too meta what grounds the grounding of
all speech and thought
um and this um is considered
to be something sacred uh because
of it it is the source of um
whatever sense we can make whatever
meaning we can make
um and it is also therefore deeply
aligned with what is
most real and uh the neoplatonic
tradition argues that it is
the place the asymptote at the horizon
where the true the good and the
beautiful converge in their common
origin and grounding so i think the
insofar as the lectio puts us
in touch with that trajectory of
transframing
that active ascension
in observation and in awareness
um is what i
think
i was touching upon in that instance of
lexia so i hope that was helpful to you
well so sorry today was uh somewhat
metaphysical
uh well what first i was very close
signed very metaphysical
and i i hope that's fine with some of
you who want some more practical
questions answered
uh we we do move around it's a rich
ecology of questions
i think which is very appropriate since
we have a rich
and growing ecology of practices and a
rich and growing sangha
so i appreciate
the quality of the questions that are
being asked
they often at this for me things that i
would not have come to
on my own so i much appreciative of that
thank you very much i want to thank you
all for joining
i want to thank my dear friend and
techno major bar my beloved son jason
who's behind the scene pinch hitting and
apprenticing with amar
to learn how to take over for those days
when mark can't be here
please subscribe to the channel to be
notified of the next video
you will also find on their links to the
lecture series awakening for the meeting
crisis
and the dialogue series voices with
ravinki just had a really astonishing
one
uh with jonathan pajot i'm really
grateful for jonathan
um for that contribution that discussion
a conversation
a true deal of this with jonathan um so
you'll find the themes talked about in
this course there
you'll find them develop more uh put
into relation to related themes
and then the whole the overall thing
situated with an encompassing
uh framework of philia sofia
please if you can if you're not opposed
to it
please follow me on twitter because that
will make it easier
for us to upload you know
information about these streams
especially things that happen on short
term notice
please invite others who might benefit
by sharing this series
please join the discord server brad is
here mark is here i believe
uh there's link is in the description uh
they
they uh do movement practices before
they sit they said
they said i think twice a day there's
lots of discussion groups
um and i think that's everything
except to remind you that we do this
every weekday morning at 9 30 eastern
time
please remember that continuity of
practice is more important than sheer
quantity of practice
don't hold yourself to a standard of
perfection
hold your stand held yourself to a
standard of
virtuous friendship
remember there's no enemy worse
than your own mind and body but there's
no friend no true ally no
true companion path better than your own
minded body
be lamps unto yourselves into each other
take care of everyone see you tomorrow
and tomorrow we're going to add in the
arms
to the tai chi walking the meditative
walking so you'll be doing full-blown
brush knees
i look forward to that take care
everyone bye-bye
you